A Guide to the Recordings of the Virginia Supreme Court, 1969-2015
Library of Virginia
- Series IV. Video recordings of Supreme Court Oral History Interviews,, 2007-2015., Extent: 8 video recordings.
  Oral history interview with Justice W. Carrington Thompson by Norfolk State Professor of History Cassandra Newby-Alexander, 2007 November 14 (1 hour, 32 minutes; transcript available at the Supreme Court of Virginia). Justice Thompson talks about his parents and his early life in Chatham, Virginia, particularly the influence of his father; his experience as a student at Hampden-Sydney College, his professors, his religious education and the importance of his religious faith throughout his life. He talks about attending law school at the University of Virginia and being in the Navy during World War II in the South Pacific. Thompson recalls his career in Chatham as a lawyer, state legislator, and circuit court judge. He reflects on the political circumstances of his appointments to the circuit court and the Supreme Court of Virginia, and his decision to retire after serving only three years. The interview closes with Thompson's thoughts on writing opinions in two death penalty cases while he was on the court, his views on the death penalty, and his strict constructionist views on the Constitution and the role of the judiciary.
  Oral history interview with Justice Henry H. Whiting by Norfolk State Professor of History Cassandra Newby-Alexander, 2011 December 12 (1 hour, 35 minutes; transcript available at the Supreme Court of Virginia). Justice Whiting talks about his family, growing up in Winchester, Virginia; serving in the Army during World War II and witnessing the Battle of Remagen, and his thoughts on General George S. Patton, who knew his father and godfather; attending college at Virginia Tech and the University of Virginia and attending law school at the University of Virginia; and practicing law in Winchester. Toward the end of the interview, he discusses being a circuit court judge in Winchester, his appointment to the Supreme Court of Virginia, and serving on the court.
  - Oral history interview with Justice Harry L. Carrico by Arlington County Circuit Court Judge Joanne Alper, 2007 April 12. (Box X)
  - Oral history interview with Justice Harry L. Carrico by Norfolk State Professor of History Cassandra Newby-Alexander, 2007 Sept 28. (Box X)
  - Oral history interview with Justice George M. Cochran by Norfolk State Professor of History Cassandra Newby-Alexander, 2007 Mar 30. (Box X)
  - Oral history interview with Judge Barbara Milano Keenan by Norfolk State Professor of History Cassandra Newby-Alexander, 2013 June 6. (Box X)
  - Oral history interview with Justice Lawrence L. Koontz, Jr., by Gail Warren, State Law Librarian, 2013 May 17. (Box X)
  - Oral history interview with Justice Elizabeth B. Lacy by Norfolk State Professor of History Cassandra Newby-Alexander, 2015 Sept 15. (Box X)
  - Oral history interview with Justice Charles S. Russell by Arlington County Circuit Court Judge Joanne Alper, 2007 Apr 23. (Box X)
  - Oral history interview with Justice Roscoe B. Stephenson by Norfolk State Professor of History Cassandra Newby-Alexander, 2007 Apr 30. (Box X)
  - Oral history interview with Justice John Charles Thomas by Norfolk State Professor of History Cassandra Newby-Alexander, 2007 Aug 8. (Box X)
  - Oral history interview with Justice W. Carrington Thompson by Norfolk State Professor of History Cassandra Newby-Alexander, 2007 Nov 14. (Box X)
  - Oral history interview with Justice Henry H. Whiting by Norfolk State Professor of History Cassandra Newby-Alexander, 2011 Dec 12. (Box X)
- Series IV. Video recordings of Court of Appeals Oral History Interviews,, 2009-2015., Extent: 8 video recordings.
  This series includes 8 video recordings of oral history interviews with judges who served on the Virginia Court of Appeals. Oral history interviews were conducted by Cassandra Newby-Alexander, Professor of History, Norfolk State University, for the Supreme Court of Virginia Archives. The interviews were conducted for the Supreme Court of Virginia Historical Commission beginning in 2007. The Supreme Court of Virginia Historical Advisory Committee (formerly Commission) was established in 2006 to preserve and promote the history of the court. Oral history interviews of retired Supreme Court justices, Court of Appeals judges, other individuals associated with the court, and civil rights attorneys were begun in 2007 and the project is ongoing.
  Oral history interview with Judge James W. Benton, 2009 March 12, conducted at the Supreme Court Building in Richmond (2 hours, 12 minutes, transcript available at the Supreme Court of Virginia). Judge Benton discusses growing up in the Huntersville neighborhood of Norfolk, Va., attending segregated schools, participating in sit-in protests to desegregate public facilities, and being among the first African American students to attend a formerly white high school in Norfolk. He talks about attending Temple University in Philadelphia, graduate school at Northwestern University in Chicago, and law school at the University of Virginia in the late 1960s and the experience of being one of the first African Americans to attend the law school. He relates his experiences working as an attorney for the NAACP Legal Defense Fund and at the Richmond law firm of Hill, Tucker and Marsh; his work on the Norfolk school desegration court cases; and his work on business cases and housing descrimination cases in the 1970s and 1980s. Benton also talks about the circumstances leading to his appointment on the Court of Appeals of Virginia when it was established in 1985, the work of establishing the court, his approach to his role as a judge, his thoughts about writing dissenting opinions, and his views on constitutional rights and criminal cases.
  Oral history interview with Judge Samuel W. Coleman, 2013 Dec 6, conducted at the Supreme Court Building in Richmond (2 hours, 27 minutes, transcript available). Judge Coleman talks about his family's roots in Scott County and growing up in Gate City, Va., his education, law practice in Gate City, and serving as a circuit court judge. He also discusses making the transition to an appellate court judge and his experiences serving as a judge on the Court of Appeals of Virginia.
  Oral history interview with Chief Judge Walter S. Felton, Jr., 2014 Nov 7, conducted at the Supreme Court Building (1 hour, 40 minutes, transcript available). Judge Felton discusses growing up in Suffolk, attending public schools there, attending college and law school at the University of Richmond, and his career as an attorney, a professor at William and Mary, a deputry attorney in the Office of the Attorney General, Counselor to Governor James S. Gilmore, and as a judge and chief judge on the Court of Appeals of Virginia.
  Oral history interview with Judge Johanna Levenson Fitzpatrick, 2009 July 13, conducted at her home in Alexandria, Virginia (2 hours; transcript available). Judge Fiztpatrick discusses her early life and growing up in Birmingham, Alabama, where her father owned a department store; her education at Tufts University and Catholic University Law School; working as a legal aid lawyer and on revisions to the Code on neglect and abuse of children; and her work as a juvenile and domestic relations judge and her appointment to the Court of Appeals of Virginia in 1992; choosing and mentoring law clerks, the process of writing opinions, differences working as a trial judge and an appellate judge, her decision to retire in 2006, and her subsequent career as a mediator.
  Oral history interview with Judge Robert P. Frank, 2014 Dec 19, conducted at his chambers in Newport News (1 hour, 26 minutes; transcript available). Judge Frank discusses his childhood in Newport News, his family's roots in Europe and their immigration to Baltimore and Newport News; his family's connections to the Jewish community in Newport News, playing sports, attending public schools in Newport News and attending the University of Virginia. He also talks about his career, first as a lawyer in private practice with his brother, and then as juvenile and domestic relations judge, a circuit court judge, and a judge on the Court of Appeals of Virginia.
  Oral history interview with Judge James W. Haley, Jr., 2013 Sept 11, conducted at the Supreme Court Building in Richmond (1 hour, 45 minutes; transcript available). Judge Haley discusses growing up in Arlington County, Virginia, and the influence of his parents (his father was a lawyer who worked as a lobbyist for coal mines, and his mother wa an attorney for the Treasury Dept. before Haley was born) and teachers at St. Stephen's Episcopal School for Boys, Washington and Lee University, and the University of Virginia. He reflects on his experience clerking for Chief Justice Eggleston (Supreme Court of Virginia), and discusses working for Commonwealth's Attorney William Hassan and working as a county attorney in King George County, as well as his experiences in private practice and as a district, circuit and appellate judge.
  Oral history interview with Judge William H. Hodges, 2015 Mar 6, conducted at his residence in Norfolk (1 hour, 44 minutes; transcript available). Judge Hodges discusses growing up in rural Norfolk County, where his father farmed and worked as a police officer; attending Randolph Macon Military Academy in Winchester and Randolph Macon College in Ashland, and then law school at Washington and Lee. He also discusses his career practicing law in Norfolk and Chesapeake, serving in the Virginia House of Delegates and Senate, and as a circuit court judge, and his experience as one of the founding members of the Court of Appeals of Virginia.
  Oral history interview with Judge Rosemarie Annunziata, 2015 Nov 18, conducted at the Supreme Court Building in Richmond (2 hours, 53 minutes; transcipt available). Judge Annunziata discusses growing up a first-generation American in Newark and Irvington, New Jersey; her family's roots in the Puglia region of Italy; her education, including French studies at the Sorbonne, Paris, and at Yale University; working at the Montgomery Advertiser newspaper in Montgomery, Alabama, from 1963-1966; her work on the Fairfax County Planning Commission and other community work; attending law school after having a family; practicing law in Fairfax County; and her career as a circuit court and appellate judge.
  - Oral history interview with Judge James W. Benton, 2009 Mar 12. (Box X)
  - Oral history interview with Judge Samuel W. Coleman, 2013 Dec 16. (Box X)
  - Oral history interview with Judge James S. Felton, 2014 Nov 7. (Box X)
  - Oral history interview with Judge Robert P. Frank, 2014 Dec 19. (Box X)
  - Oral history interview with Judge Joanna Levenson Fitzpatrick, 2009 July 13. (Box X)
  - Oral history interview with Judge James W. Haley, Jr., 2013 Sept 11. (Box X)
  - Oral history interview with Judge William H. Hodges, 2015 Mar 6. (Box X)
  - Oral history interview with Judge Rosemarie Annunziata, 2015 Nov 18. (Box X)